<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title type="html">Index</title>
  <subtitle type="html"></subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>Administrator</name>
    <uri></uri>
  </author>

  <link href="http://mildred.fr/tags/html/" rel="alternate" />
  <link href="http://mildred.fr/tags/html/atom.xml" rel="self" />
  <generator uri="http://webgen.rubyforge.org/documentation/sourcehandler/feed.html" version="0.5.14">
    webgen - Webgen::SourceHandler::Feed
  </generator>
  <updated>2013-02-14T18:18:57+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://mildred.fr/tags/html/</id>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html">HTML 2.0: Why I think HTML is broken</title>
    
    <author>
      <name>Shanti</name>
      <uri></uri>
    </author>
    
    <link href="http://mildred.fr/Blog/2011/08/05/html_2_0/index.html" rel="alternate" />
    <id>http://mildred.fr/Blog/2011/08/05/html_2_0/index.html</id>
    <updated>2012-04-10T16:57:20+02:00</updated>
    
    <published>2011-08-05T10:35:08+02:00</published>
    
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;First postulate: HTML was designed as a stateless protocol&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Context: web sites need to maintain a context (or state) to track the client.
This is required by the log-in procedures the various websites have. It is also
useful to track the user in a web store, to know which items the user wants to
buy. In fact, it is requires almost everywhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first solution to be thrown out for this problem are the cookies. People
didn't like cookies but now, everyone accepts them. Nothing works without
cookies. Why did people dislike cookies back then? They liked their provacy and
cookies makes it possible to track the user. Through advertisement networks, the
advertiser known exactly which website the user visited. And it is still the
case now. What changed is that the users got tried to fight cookies and have
every website break, and they got used to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;People got used to being tracked&lt;/strong&gt; just as people are used to be watched by
video cameras in the street and people are used to get tracked by the government
and big companies and banks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cookies are a great way to track prople, all because HTTP didn't include session
management. The way Google track you is very simple. Google Analytics puts a
cookie on your computer and each time you access the Google Server, they know
it's the same person. Google is everywhere:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Many web sites are using Google APIs, or the jQuery library at Google.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Many web sites ask Google to track their users to know how many prople visit
their page.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Google makes advertisement.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Youtube, Blogger, Picasa and others are owned by Google&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;With this alone, Google is found on almost every page. If you have an account at
Google (YouTube, Picase, Gmail, Blogger, Android or other), they can even give a
name or an e-mail address to all of these information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Google motto is &lt;em&gt;Don't be Evil&lt;/em&gt;, they are perhaps not evil but can they become
evil? Yes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whatever, my dream HTTP 2.0 protocol would include of course push support like
WebSockets, but more importantly: session management. How should this be done?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;HTTP and Session Management&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;When the server needs a session, it initiates the session by giving a session
token to the client.&lt;/strong&gt; The client needs to protect this token from being stolen
and should display that a session is in pogress for this website. It could
appear on the URL bar for example. The client could close the session at any
moment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the token, the server provides its validity scope. Domains, subdomains,
path. Only the resources in the session scope will receive the tocken back. If
for example &lt;code&gt;http://example.com&lt;/code&gt; starts a session at &lt;code&gt;example.com&lt;/code&gt; but have an
&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;iframe&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; that includes facebook. Facebook won't receive the session token. If
Facebook wants to start a session (because the user wants to log-in) it will
start a second session.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Session cannot escape the page. If you have two tabs open with facebook in each
tab (either full page or embedded), the two facebook instances don't share the
same session, unless the user explicitely allowed this. For instance, when
Facebook starts a session, the browser could tell the user that Facebook already
have an existing session and the user would be free to choose between the new
session and the existing one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;How does this solve XSS&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;XSS is when a website you don't trust access the session of a website you trust,
and steal it. At least I think so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With this kind of session management, the session couldn't possibly be stolen.
Suppose that the non-trusted site makes an XmlHttpRequest to gmail.com. If
cross-domain wasn't forbidden, any web-site could read your mails.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the new session management, if the untrusted site makes a request to
gmail.com, gmail.com session wouldn't be available and the login page would be
returned instead of the list of e-mails. If the non trusted website tries to
log-in, you would be prompted to associate the Gmail session with the site you
don't trust. If you aren't completely idion, you wouldn't allow the online
pharmacy to connect to Gmail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Extra&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What is known about you?&lt;/strong&gt; Let's take an average person that uses her credit
card, have and Android phone with Gmail, uses Facebook:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;All your relationships are known by Google (Gmail, Google+) and Facebook&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;All your interests are known by Google and Facebook (Ad Sense track which
website you visit and Facebook have a huge profile on you)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;All your posessions are known to your bank&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Your photograph is known by Google and Facebook (people probably took a
photo of you and placed it on their Android phone synchronized with Google)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Your location is known (using your Android phone, your credit card, or your
RFID card you use for public transportation)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;...&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If you ever want to keep private, it is becoming very difficult.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
