<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>Index</title>
    <link>http://mildred.fr/tags/wwwgen/"</link>
    <description></description>
    <pubDate>Thu, 14 Feb 2013 18:19:54 +0100</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 14 Feb 2013 18:19:54 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>webgen - Webgen::SourceHandler::Feed</generator>

    
    <item>
      <title>wwwgen: imagined architecture</title>
      <link>http://mildred.fr/Blog/2012/09/13/wwwgen_imagined_architecture/index.html</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I started writing wwwgen: a website generator that uses redo for its
dependency tracking. Unfortunately, I might not have taken the correct
approach to the problem. I reuse the webgen concepts, and that might be
a bad idea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Specifically, webgen (and my first version of wwwgen) are bottom-up
systems (you take the sources and build everything they can generate).
The problem is that redo itself is top-down (you take the target and
build it, building sources as they are needed), and I tried to make the
two match. It's very difficult, and impossible to do with a clean design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I'd like to have is a simple &lt;code&gt;wwwgen&lt;/code&gt; binary that generates a HTML
file from a source file. Let's imagine how it could work:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;If the source file is a simple page with no templates, just generate
the HTML and this is it&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;If the source file is a simple page with a template, redo-ifchange the
template source and build the HTML combining the two&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;If the source file is an index, we have a problem because multiple
outputs are generated. Redo doesn't support this case and we must find a
way to make it work.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So, we have a problem here ...&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, we have another problem. Specifically, my source file is called
&lt;code&gt;title.page&lt;/code&gt; and I want my output file to be &lt;code&gt;title/index.html&lt;/code&gt;. In
webgen, this is implemented by a configuration in &lt;code&gt;title.page&lt;/code&gt; telling
it to build in &lt;code&gt;title/index.html&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a solution to solve both problems at once. the wwwgen command
creates an archive (the formats needs to be defined, it could be tar, or
different yaml documents in the same file for example). Then, the build
process would be:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;all.do&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt; find src -name &quot;*.src&quot; \
   | sed 's/src$/gen/' \
   | xargs -d '\n' redo-ifchange
 find src -name &quot;*.gen&quot; \
   | xargs -d '\n' wwwgen unpack
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;default.gen.do&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt; redo-ifchange &quot;$2.src&quot;
 wwwgen --redo-dependencies -o &quot;$3&quot; generate &quot;$2.src&quot;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;wwwgen generate&lt;/code&gt; would parse the source file and generate an archive,
that will be unpacked later by &lt;code&gt;wwwgen unpack&lt;/code&gt;. Let's see how it can work:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The source file can choose where it unpacks, relatively to the
directory where the source file is&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;If the source file is an index, it will redo-ifchange the other source
files for the index and redo-ifchange the template, generate multiple
pages packed together.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;If the source file is a tag tree (a special source that doesn't output
anything on its own but create index files dynamically), then it parses
every child to find a canonical list of tags and the paths they refer
to. Then, it creates the index files. Unfortunately, those index files
will never be compiled until next build.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;How an we improve the design to be able to create source files dynamically.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are different views to the problem:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;pages, index and tags should all generate all the output files they
are related to. It means that index files should be able to generate
pages, and tags should be able to generate indexes and pages.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;pages should generate the output file, index should generate pages and
feeds and tags should generate index.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;mixed solution (the one described): pages generate output file, index
should generate the output files as well and tags generates index.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;How can we generate source files on the fly:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;have a predefined compilation order: first tags, then index and lastly
feeds and pages.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;rebuild everything until no more source files are generated. We might
build unnecessary things.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I prefer the second solution which is more flexible, but we need a way
to avoid building things twice. For example, it's not necessary to build
a page if on the next phase the page source is going to be regenerated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Very simply, the generated page can contain a link to the index source
file that generated it, and when generating the page, &lt;code&gt;redo-ifchange&lt;/code&gt; is
run on the index file.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next question: what if a tag is deleted. The corresponding index page is
going to stay around until the next clean. The tag page should keep
around a list of index files it generated and delete them when a tag is
no longer detected. And deleting the index should not be done using &lt;code&gt;rm&lt;/code&gt;
because the index will need to delete the pages it generated. The best
solution would be to integrate to redo to detect these files.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The build scripts now are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;all.do&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt; oldsrclist=
 srclist=&quot;$(find src -name &quot;*.src&quot;)&quot;
 while [ &quot;$oldsrclist&quot; != &quot;$srclist&quot; ]; do
   echo &quot;$srclist&quot; \
     | sed 's/src$/gen/' \
     | xargs -d '\n' redo-ifchange
   oldsrclist=&quot;$srclist&quot;
   srclist=&quot;$(find src -name &quot;*.src&quot;)&quot;
 done

 find src -name &quot;*.gen&quot; \
   | xargs -d '\n' wwwgen unpack
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;default.gen.do&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt; redo-ifchange &quot;$2.src&quot;
 wwwgen --redo-dependencies -o &quot;$3&quot; generate &quot;$2.src&quot;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
</description>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Oct 2012 21:03:17 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://mildred.fr/Blog/2012/09/13/wwwgen_imagined_architecture/index.html</guid>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>WWWGen : Static Page Generator and Beyond</title>
      <link>http://mildred.fr/Blog/2012/07/26/wwwgen_static_page_generator_and_beyond/index.html</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I want to create a new static webpage generator. There are tons of them,
you'll tell me, why do I want to create a new one?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Static Website Generator&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let's see what we have:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;webby: my first love&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;nanoc: the second one I used&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;webgen: the one I'm using currently (with tons of local modifications)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;jekyll: powering GitHub pages&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;and many more most probably&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Most of these systems take the assumption that you are a developer and
you are comfortable to write code to have your website running. In all
of these systems, I was forced to code some Ruby here and there to get
it working how I wanted to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The case of nanoc3 is very special because the main configuration uses a
special Ruby DSL to manage the path locations. If you have non technical
users, they won't be willing to write code in this file anyway. And for
technical users, it might not be powerful enough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jekyll is probably the simplest system and can probably be used by non
technical users, but it is far too simple and not powerful enough.
That's why I didn't used it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the end, I modified Webgen a lot to include the following features:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ability to write ruby code in haml instead on having to rely on the
template engine included in webgen&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;special .index nodes that will generate a paginated index of articles
found dynamically. The index would contain the last articles in reverse
order while the pages will contain each N articles in the natural order.
This way, an article that end up on page 3 is always going to be on page 3.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;special .tags nodes that will generate .index pages dynamically to
create an index or articles for each tag.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If you look around, there are not many static web page generators that
permit that. First, I decided I would maintain my own version of webgen
with these modifications, but now, I have the idea that the code base is
so horrible that I prefer rewrite the same functions from scratch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Rewriting From Scratch&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I said, I'm not satisfied with the current status of the webgen code.
There is a complex system of cache, and a blackboard object that is used
to dispatch method call to the correct objects around the system. The
problem is that this extra indirection level makes it difficult to know
the code path. It would be useful if the hooks in the blackboard would
be highly dynamic, but it's mostly static. it serves no purpose whatsoever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moreover, I don't like big programs that do everything. And all of these
static website generators have a component that is used to determine
which pages are out of date, and only update them. This is traditionally
what make(1) should do. And recently, I found that
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/apenwarr/redo/&quot;&gt;redo&lt;/a&gt; does the job very well. So, I want it to be an integral
part of my new system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;WWWSupport&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently, I wrote a piece of code: &lt;a href=&quot;http://git.mildred.fr/?p=pub/mildred/wwwsupport.git;a=tree&quot;&gt;WWWSupport&lt;/a&gt;. It's a very
simple git repository that is supposed to be included as a submodule of
the git repository of a website. it contains a
&lt;a href=&quot;http://cr.yp.to/daemontools.html&quot;&gt;daemontools&lt;/a&gt; daemon that receives e-mail from a special
mailbox and convert them into blog posts on the fly (that's how I'm
currently writing this block post).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want my WWWGen project to integrate the same way into my website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;WWWGen&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;WWWGen is the name of my website generator. The architecture is very simple:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A &lt;code&gt;src&lt;/code&gt; directory containing the pages, in the same format as webgen&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A &lt;code&gt;nodes&lt;/code&gt; directory containing the files WWWGen is working on to
generate output&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An output directory where the result files in &lt;code&gt;nodes&lt;/code&gt; is copied to,
and where some static assets are copied as well (using rsync)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A redo script &lt;code&gt;all.do&lt;/code&gt; that contains the configuration and invokes the
wwwgen script.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The wwwgen script will create the &lt;code&gt;nodes&lt;/code&gt; directory and the redo scripts
necessary to its working in it. Then, it will do three things:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;For each source file, the script will create:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A .node file that contain a relative path to the source file, and
represents it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;As many .outdep files as the source file will generate output
files. The .outdep file is not managed by redo (because redo doesn't
support multiple targets yet). It references the .node file using a
relative path.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;  Note that during this process, new sources can be generated to allow
to create new nodes. This step will be executed until no new sources are
generated.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Once this is done, the main script will look for all of the .outdep
files and will build the corresponding .out file. The .out file will
contain the final processed result of the page&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Copy all .out files in the output directory (after removing the .out
extension) and all the static files in the static directory.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Note that step 1 and 2 recursively call redo to generate the .node and
.out files. This two step design is necessary to account for multiple
pages generated from a single source.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Beyond&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In all my projects, I always want to focus on the usability of what I
create. I always think that non programmers should be able to do the
same that I did, to a certain limit. For example, my personal e-mail
server at home is scripted all the way. Reinstalling it should be a
matter of:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;installing a debian system with a basic configuration&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;clone my git repositories&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Set some basic configuration (hostname, ...)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;run &lt;code&gt;redo install&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I agree that even then, not anybody can install at home a mail server,
but with a process that simple, it's possible to create user interfaces
for it. So even if it's not there, it's a possibility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want the same for WWWGen. It leaves a possibility for creating a user
interface. Nothing prevents from creating a web application or even a
native application, that will create markdown pages with a WYSIWYG
editor (à la WordPress). The page files thus created could be checked
out in a git repository and pushed to a server. There, a hook will run
WWWGen to update the website with the modifications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This could be seriously a very good alternative to WordPress, and I'd
preefer working with such a system than WordPress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;What already exists&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am not very good at creating desktop applications. So I thought I
would reuse the existing ones : my mailer. I's like a Content Management
System where everything must be configured by hand, and only articles
can be submitted using an e-mail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is being sent by e-mail to my personal web server. Currently,
I'm still using plain text with a markdown syntax, but we could reuse
the HTML markup in a mail. This e-mail is then processed by a special
alias in &lt;code&gt;/etc/aliases&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt; http.www: &quot;|/srv/http/www/wwwsupport/push.sh&quot;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This line was automatically generated by an install.do script. The
push.sh script will read the mail using a ruby script and will create a
file in my website git repository with the content of the mail. Then
webgen is run and the content of the repository is pushed to origin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a consequence, the new article appears on the website. This is a very
simple form of user interface, but it permits anybody to write blog posts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;What features I would like to see&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Better parsing of HTML e-mail&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Using wwwgen instead of webgen&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Support for image galleries using git-annex in wwwgen&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Support for taking the attached images in an e-mail to create a
gallery on my website?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;h2&gt;What features a customer would want&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A web application that can :&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;modify the website configuration in the &lt;code&gt;all.do&lt;/code&gt; file&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;modify any source files, using a WYSIWYG editor when applicable&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;add static assets (possibly using git-annex)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;run the website compilation and preview it&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;push to a server to update the production website&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is entirely possible.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Oct 2012 21:03:17 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://mildred.fr/Blog/2012/07/26/wwwgen_static_page_generator_and_beyond/index.html</guid>
    </item>
    

  </channel>
</rss>



