<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>Index</title>
    <link>http://mildred.fr/tags/privacy/"</link>
    <description></description>
    <pubDate>Thu, 14 Feb 2013 18:19:34 +0100</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 14 Feb 2013 18:19:34 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>webgen - Webgen::SourceHandler::Feed</generator>

    
    <item>
      <title>Blueprints for a Privacy Respecting Browser</title>
      <link>http://mildred.fr/Blog/2011/10/19/blueprints_for_a_privacy_respecting_browser/index.html</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;What is this all about: web privacy. We are tracked everywhere, and i'd like to
help if possible. So, let's design a web browser that for once respects your
privacy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Main features:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Each website has its own cookie jar, its own cache and its own HTML5 local
storage&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;History related css attributes are disabled&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;External plugins are only enabled on demand&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Support for Tor/I2P is enabled by default&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You have complete control over who receives what information&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Let's you control in the settings if you want to allow referrers or not.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The contextual menu let's you open links anonymously (no referrer, anonymous
session)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The browser is bundled with a particular UI that let you control everything
during your browsing session. it is non intrusive and makes the best choice by
default. I am thinking of a notification bar that shows at the bottom. I noticed
that this place is not intrusive when I realized that the search bar in Firefox
was most of the time open, even if most of the time I didn't use it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, let's define a session:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A session can be used my more than one domain at the same time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A session is associated to a specific cache storage&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A session is associated to a specific HTML5 storage&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A session is associated to a specific cookie jar&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A session acn be closed. When it is closed, session cookies are deleted from
the session&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A session can be reopened. All long lasting cookies, cache, HTML5 storage
and such is then used again.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A session can be anonymous. In such a case, the session is deleted
completely when it is closed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A session is associated to none, one or more domains. These domains are the
domains the end user can see in the address bar, not the sub items in the
page.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Sessions are like Firefox profiles. If you iopen a new session, it's like you
opened a new Firefox profile you just created. Because people will never create
a different Firefox profile for each site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we want to protect privacy, when a link is opened, a new session should be
created each time. To make it usable to browse web sites, it is made possible to
share sessions in specific cases. Let's define the cases where it might be
intelligent to share a profile:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;You click a link or submit a form and expect to still be logged-in in the
site you are viewing. You don't care if you follow a link to an external
page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;User Interface: If the link matches one of the domains of the session, then
keep the session. No UI. If the user wanted a new session, the &quot;Open
anonymously&quot; entry in the context menu exists. A button on the toolbar might
be available to enter a state where we always want to open links
anonymously.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the link points to another domain, then open the link in a new session
unless &quot;Open in the same session&quot; was specified in the context menu. The UI
contains:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;We Protected your privacy by separating &amp;lt;domain of the new site&amp;gt; from
the site you were visiting previously (&amp;lt;domain of the previous site&amp;gt;).

Choices: [ (1) Create a new anonymous session          | ▼ ]
         | (2) Continue session from &amp;lt;previous domain&amp;gt; |
         | (3) Use a previous session for &amp;lt;new domain&amp;gt; |
         | (4) Use session from bookmark &quot;&amp;lt;name&amp;gt;&quot;      |
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first choice is considered the default and the page is loaded with it.
If the user chooses a new option, then the page is reloaded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the user chooses (2), the page is reloaded with the previous session and
the user will be asked if &quot;Do you want &lt;old domain&gt; and &lt;new domain&gt; to have
access to the same private information about you?&quot;. Answers are Yes, No and
Always. If the answer is Always, then in the configuration, the two domains
are considered one and the same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The choice (3) will use the most recent session for the new domain. It might
be a session currently in use or a session in the history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are as many (4) options as there are bookmarks for the new domain. If
different bookmarks share a single session, only one bookmark is shown. This
choice will load the session from the bookmark.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If (3) and (4) are the same sessions, and there is only one bookmark (4),
then the (4) option is left out.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;You use a bookmark and expect to continue the session you had for this
bookmark (webmails)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The session is simpely stored in the bookmark. When saving a bookmark, there
is an option to store the session with it or not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;[X] Do not save any personal information with this bookmark
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;You open a new URL and you might want reuse a session that was opened for
this URL.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The User Interface allows you to restore the session:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;We protected your privacy by not sending any personal information to
&amp;lt;domain&amp;gt;. If you want &amp;lt;domain&amp;gt; to receive private information, please
select:

Choices: [ Do not send private information     | ▼ ]
         | Use a previous session for &amp;lt;domain&amp;gt; |
         | Use session from bookmark &quot;&amp;lt;name&amp;gt;&quot;  |
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If you can see other use cases, please comment on that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From these use cases, I can infer three kind of sessions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Live sessions, currently in use&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Saved sessions, associated to a bookmark&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Closed sessions in the past, accessible using history. Collected after a too
long time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Now, how to implement that? I was thinking of QtWebKit as I already worked with
Qt and it's easy to work with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We have a main widget: &lt;code&gt;QWebView&lt;/code&gt;. We want to change the session when a new
page is loaded. So we hook up with the signal &lt;code&gt;loadStarted&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We prevent history related CSS rules by implementing &lt;code&gt;QWebHistoryInterface&lt;/code&gt;,
more specifically, we store the history necessary to implement
&lt;code&gt;QWebHistoryInterface&lt;/code&gt; in the session.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We change the cache by implementing &lt;code&gt;QAbstractNetworkCache&lt;/code&gt; and setting it
using &lt;code&gt;view-&amp;gt;page()-&amp;gt;networkAccessManager()-&amp;gt;setCache(...)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We change the cookie jar by implementing &lt;code&gt;QNetworkCookieJar&lt;/code&gt; and setting it
using &lt;code&gt;view-&amp;gt;page()-&amp;gt;networkAccessManager()-&amp;gt;setCookieJar(...)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Change the local storage path using a directory dedicated for the session
and using &lt;code&gt;view-&amp;gt;page()-&amp;gt;settings()-&amp;gt;setLocalStoragePath(QString)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;After all that, we'll have to inspect the resulting browser to determine if
there are still areas where we fail at protecting privacy.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Apr 2012 16:57:20 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://mildred.fr/Blog/2011/10/19/blueprints_for_a_privacy_respecting_browser/index.html</guid>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bug 660340 - Due to constant threats on privacy, epiphany should allow the user to have multiple separate session running</title>
      <link>http://mildred.fr/Blog/2011/09/28/bug_660340_-_due_to_constant_threats_on_privacy_epiphany_should_allow_the_user_to_have_multiple_separate_session_running/index.html</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Here is my &lt;a href=&quot;https://bugzilla.gnome.org/show_bug.cgi?id=660340&quot;&gt;Bug 660340&lt;/a&gt;. I
created it after looking at the recent facebook 'enhancements' that makes
privacy even more precious (&lt;a href=&quot;http://linuxfr.org/news/facebook-f8-timeline-musiquevid%C3%A9o-ticker-boutons-et-les-cons%C3%A9quences-pour-le-web&quot;&gt;article in French&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to quickly find a way to preserve our privacy on the Internet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hi,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the recent threats of the various big internet companies on our privacy,
it would be a great enhancement if epiphany allowed to have separate navigation
contexts (cookies, HTML5 storage, cache) at will, and easily.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some companies, especially facebook, and I suppose Google could do that as
well, can use all kind of methods to track a user usiquely. using cache, HTML5
storage or cookies. I wonder if they can use the cache as well, but I heard it
could be prevented. Firefox does.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One solution to counter these privacy threats is to have a different browser,
or different browser profile, for each of the web sites we load. This is
however very inconvenient, and it should made easily possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First let define the concept of session. A session is almost like a separate
instance of the browser. It share bookmark and preferences with other session,
but have separate cache, separate set of cookies and separate HTML5 DOM
storage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I imagine the following behaviour, based on the document.domain of the toplevel
document:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;If a page is loaded without referrer, and the domain is not associated with
an existing session, start a new session for that domain&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;If a page is loaded without referrer, and the domain is a domain that is
already associated with an existing session, then prompt non intrusively:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;&quot;You already opened a session on example.com.&quot;
Choices: [  Start a new session    ▼ ] [Use this session]
         [[ New anonymous session   ]]
         [  Replace existing session ]
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the session is started anonymously, it would not be considered for reuse&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;If a page is loaded using a link from an existing window/tab, and the
domain
is the same, then share the session&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;If a page is loaded using a link from an existing window/tab, and the
domain
is NOT the same and, then a non intrusive message is displayed:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;&quot;You are now visiting example2.com. Do you want to continue your session
from example1.com?&quot;
Choices: [  Start a new session    ▼ ] [Share previous session]
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &quot;Start a new session&quot; dropdown menu changes if the example2.com is
already associated with a session or not. If example2.com is associated
with a session:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt; [[ New anonymous session            ]]
 [  Replace example2.com session      ]
 [  Use existing example2.com session ]
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If example2.com is not associated with a session:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt; [[ New anonymous session    ]]
 [  New example2.com session  ]
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The choices in [[xxx]] (as opposed to [xxx]) is the most privacy enhancing one,
and would be the default if the user choose in the preferences&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;[x] allow me not to be tracked
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The messages are non intrusive, they can be displayed as a banner on top of the
page. The page is first loaded with the default choice, and if the user decides
to use the other choice, the page will be reloaded accordingly (or the session
will be reassigned).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This setting can traditionally be used to set the do not track header&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every settings should have a setting &quot;do not prompt me again&quot; that could be
reset at some point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;About embedded content: Because toplevel pages do not share the same session
(toplevel page opened at example.com have a different session than toplevel
page opened at blowmyprivacy.org), if a page from example.com have embedded
content from blowmyprivacy.org, the embedded content would not be able to track
the user, except within the example.com website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is possible to imagine global settings that would hide some complexity:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;[ ] When I load a page, always associate it with its existing session.
[ ] When I switch website, always reuse the existing session of the new
    website.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This user interface might seem complex at first, but it is far less complex
than letting the user deal with different browser profiles by hand.
Unfortunately, I don't think we can abstract privacy that easily. Keep in mind
that all of these settings would be enabled only if the user choose to enable
privacy settings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am ready to contribute to the implementation of this highly important feature
(important for our future and our privacy). Do you think an extension might be
able to do all of that, or do you think the browser code should be modified?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Further possible enhancements:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Add another choice for anonymous sessions using Tor (or I2P)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Add the possibility to have multiple session registered with the same
domain. This would enable the user to have different profiles for the same
website.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Apr 2012 16:57:20 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://mildred.fr/Blog/2011/09/28/bug_660340_-_due_to_constant_threats_on_privacy_epiphany_should_allow_the_user_to_have_multiple_separate_session_running/index.html</guid>
    </item>
    

  </channel>
</rss>



